Guide to the WYBC, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
WYBC, Yale University, records
1941-1984
RU 59
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
46.03
(95 boxes)
The records consist of correspondence, scripts, schedules, logs, training materials, meeting minutes, policies and bylaws, contracts, articles, printed matter, photographs, and audiotapes that document the programming, operations and governance of WYBC, Yale's undergraduate radio station.
WYBC (Radio station: New Haven, Conn.)
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from WYBC, 1988 and 1990; gift of Joel Levitch, 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in box 95 are closed until January 1, 2047 as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in five series: I. Correspondence, 1947-1974. II. Programming, 1945-1984. III. Operations and Administrative Files, 1941-1971. IV. Advertising, 1954-1986. V. Audiorecording, circa 1962-1981.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, scripts, schedules, logs, training materials, meeting minutes, policies and bylaws, contracts, articles, printed matter, photographs, and audiotapes that document the programming, operations and governance of WYBC, Yale's undergraduate radio station. In addition to documenting WYBC's general history and development, programming records, correspondence, and training materials provide insight into evolving musical and theatrical tastes, Yale's changing relationship with women, and the undergraduate apprenticeship system of "heeling." News reports and editorials also document campus events and student sentiments. Of particular interest are the news broadcasts and reporter notes from WYBC's live broadcast of student protests on the New Haven Green during May 1970. Station records also document changes in WYBC policy and personnel regarding African-American programming and WYBC's role in the New Haven community.
Biographical / Historical
WYBC was established as Yale University's undergraduate radio station in the winter of 1940-1941 through alumni financial support. The station's original call letters were WOCD, standing for "Oldest College Daily," because the station was administered and operated by the Yale Daily News and housed in the Daily 's building. On September 22, 1941, WOCD began to broadcast music, news, Yale-interest programs on a closed-circuit AM channel into the university's residential colleges. During World War II, paper shortages and Yale's accelerated academic schedule forced the Daily to curtail its activities extensively, but the Dean of the College asked WOCD to continue its full schedule of news reports and bulletins. During this period, the Navy also used WOCD to teach Morse Code. WOCD steadily increased the size of its audience and staff and broke off its relationship with the Daily in 1944-1945.
After its split from the Daily, WOCD changed its frequency from 905 to 640 and moved its studios to 193 York Street. On March 26, 1945, Microphone, the station's newsletter, announced in its first issue the station's new call letters, WYBC (Yale Broadcasting Company). For the next couple of years, WYBC was dedicated to purchasing technical equipment and increasing its programming to include sports, musical, non-musical, dramatic, and news/political shows. On November 19, 1947, WYBC moved to its current studios in Hendrie Hall on Elm Street.
On April 16, 1948, the Yale Broadcasting Company (YBC) was incorporated in the state of Connecticut as a non-profit, tax-exempt organization. Under its Articles of Incorporation, YBC declared its intention to continue to serve the Yale student community while conforming to standard operating procedures of the Federal Communications Commission (FCC) and the National Association of Broadcasters. At its original founding, WYBC had become a member of the Intercollegiate Broadcasting System, a professional organization that promoted college radio stations. WYBC found this organization increasingly unsatisfactory and in February 1948, with Dartmouth College Radio, formed the Ivy Network, of which all Ivy League college stations became members. The Ivy Network assisted member stations in program exchanges and other aspects of broadcasting.
During the 1950s, WYBC expanded its activities beyond programming, such as the production of a successful record album of performances by Yale singing groups from the popular live concert program, Yale Sings. Also, beginning in 1953, the station began a brief venture into television with WYBC-TV, the nation's first student owned and operated station. Shows were aired simultaneously on the radio and television and included lectures from notable Yale professors, dramatic and musical performances by Yale students, a panel show, and an interview program. WYBC-TV ended broadcasting in 1955 due to problems with WYBC's radio cables. During 1954, WYBC broadcast the Yale-Harvard football game to 53 Yale clubs across the country. The next year, WYBC nationally broadcast Yale football games against Army, Princeton, and Harvard.
Another effort to expand station operations was the creation of WYBC-A (AM 540), a companion closed-circuit station, in 1955. WYBC-A was plagued by problems and operated for only two months. In early 1957, new WYBC efforts resulted in the return of WYBC-A. One station broadcast thirteen hours a day and the other station broadcast twelve hours. WYBC-A existed until 1968. These dual AM stations allowed WYBC to be on the air twenty-four hours a day. On March 9, 1959, WYBC also began broadcasting from WYBC-FM (FM 94.3).
The 1960s brought greater technical development of WYBC when Yale built recording studios for the station in 1964. In 1966, WYBC-FM converted to a stereo multiplex station. The station's staff also began to change as students became attracted to the "Counterculture". This cultural shift was the basis for Gary Trudeau's Doonsbury cartoon radio station "WBBY," a laid-back, liberal college station. In 1968, a reassessment of WYBC's broader community role brought non-students into the station staff for the first time. News and political programs expanded as well as African-American programming intended to increase coverage of African-American news stories and to appeal to minority communities. During the trials of Black Panther leaders in spring of 1970, station reporters conducted live broadcasts from the New Haven Green during widespread student protests.
During the late 1970s and 1980s, WYBC fell into financial trouble due to declining student interest and lower advertising revenues. In 1992, WYBC relocated its transmitter to West Rock and hired a professional staff to increase the station's professionalism and audience size. In 1994, WYBC signed a joint sales agreement with General Broadcasting of Connecticut, Inc. to improve advertising sales and ensure WYBC's financial stability. Currently, WYBC operates FM and AM stations and broadcasts original music, news, and sports programs.
Yale daily news -- History; College radio stations; Journalism, College; Radio advertising; Radio programs; Radio scripts; Radio stations -- History; Radio stations; WYBC (Radio station: New Haven, Conn.); Yale University -- Students
- Correspondence, 1947-1974; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains incoming and outgoing letters to external parties, memoranda, and telegrams that detail the programming, financial, and administrative activities of WYBC as well as the station's relationship with other local and college radio stations, advertisers, suppliers, and audience. The series also contains individual correspondence files of some WYBC Board chairmen and station personnel. The records are arranged alphabetically within headings based on WYBC's own classification: General, Board chairmen, Station personnel, Other radio stations, Operations, and Other. For internal station correspondence, see Series III. Operations and Administration Files, under the heading, Intra-station correspondence, memoranda, and reports. Additional correspondence of a topical nature is also scattered throughout Series II. Programming, Series III. Operations and Administrative Files, and Series IV. Advertising.
  - General, 1947-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 8)
  - Board chairmen
    - Becton, Henry and Edward Marshner, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Brooks, Clint [includes executive committee minutes], 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ellis, Charles D., 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Suttcliffe, Harold E. and Thomas F. Stroock [vice chairman], 1947-1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Station personnel
    - General, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 18 - 19)
    - Music director, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Soloway, Bruce [station manager], 1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Weingarth, Gordon [program director], 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Other radio stations
    - Ivy Network, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Local New Haven stations, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - WELI [New Haven], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - WDBS [Dartmouth], 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - WHRB [Harvard], 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - WPRU [Princeton], 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - WVBR [Cornell], 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - WXPN [Pennsylvania], 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Women's college stations, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Other college stations, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Operations
    - Advertising, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Board of governors, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Internal improvements, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Perspective, WYBC - Yale Daily News forum, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Photo department, 1953-1954 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Recording division, 1949-1951 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Supervisors, 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Various problems, including station interference, obscenities, lawsuit, finances, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Yale administration, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Other
    - American Broadcasting Company news, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Letters from WYBC listeners, 1954-1962 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Public service, 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - RCA Victor, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - This Is College Radio [film], 1956 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Programming, 1945-1984; Series II
  This series contains records that document WYBC programs and shows from the 1940s through 1980s. These records are arranged alphabetically within headings based on the structure of WYBC's programming departments: Sports programming; Musical programming; Non-musical programming; Dramatic programming; News and political programming; and African-American programming. The series also includes headings related to the radio station's public service, public relations, and general programming activities.
  Sports programming includes scripts, schedules, correspondence, and publications that were used to broadcast Yale athletic events. This heading also contains records related to the Yale Sports Network, the general sports broadcasting unit of WYBC, and a survey the Network sent to Yale alumni regarding interest in broadcasting football games.
  Musical programming contains scripts and schedules of recorded music shows produced by WYBC, live broadcasts of Yale and other college music groups, and broadcasts of syndicated programs. The heading includes files of the WYBC Record Department and records related to concerts organized by WYBC.
  Non-musical programming contains scripts and schedules of talk and call-in shows produced by WYBC or syndicated nationally. The subject matter of these shows include general editorials, relations with the New Haven community, cinema, freshman orientation to Yale, and English literature.
  Dramatic programming contains scripts and schedules from various theatrical programs and broadcasts of plays. The heading also contains scripts for dramatic programs as well as information about station activities for American Brotherhood Week.
  News and political programming contains press releases, teletype transcripts, correspondence, scripts, reporters' notes, and newspaper articles that were used to broadcast local, state and national news in general reports and regular news programs. Political program records include reports on local forums and debates and coverage of elections from 1956 to 1970. The heading also contains extensive scripts, reporter notes, press releases and fliers related to the 1969-1970 trials of New Haven Black Panther leaders and subsequent student demonstrations on the New Haven Green that occurred during May 1970.
  African-American programming contains records documenting WYBC's expansion of its programming to include African-American community issues during the late 1960's. This heading includes WYBC programming policy statements; records outlining the structure of the African-American programming department; newspaper articles and press releases; copies of the African-American newspaper The New Haven Star; news reports and reporter notes regarding Black Panther Lonnie McLucas's 1970 trial; and scripts from radio programs.
  Other headings include: Public service projects, which contains correspondence and schedules related to WYBC's involvement in community drives and other charity events; Public relations, which contains correspondence, audience surveys and data, and notes related to station publicity; and General programming information, which contains operating procedures, program schedules, staff lists, Federal Communications Commission regulations, and some training materials.
  - Sports programming
    - General, 1949-1952 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Baseball, 1948-1952 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Basketball, 1947-1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Football, 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hockey, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Quarterback Corner, 1947-1951 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Quarterback Corner, Time Out, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Time Out, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Yale sports network
      - General, 1957-1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Alumni club surveys, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10 - 13)
      - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Yale Club of New York, 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Musical programming
    - Shows
      - Cavalcade of Music, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - College Sound at Carnegie Hall, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Library of Congress concerts, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Love in Six Languages, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Music school broadcasts, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Musical Show Window, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - Smoke Rings, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - Songs from Broadway Musicals, 1948-1952 (Box 5, Folder 24 - 25)
      - Songs from New England Colleges, 1949-1950 (Box 5, Folder 26)
      - Sunday at the Opera, Golden Moments at the Opera, 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 27)
      - Sunday Classical Notes
        - General, 1979-1982 (Box 5, Folder 28)
        - Microphone breaks, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
        - Playlists, 1978-1982 (Box 5, Folder 30 - 31)
        - Program guide and record orders, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 32)
        - Public service announcements and advertisements, 1980-1983 (Box 5, Folder 33 - 34)
      - Symphony Hall, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Yale band concerts, 1947-1952 (Box 5, Folder 36)
      - Yale Sings, 1947-1952 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - Yale Sings, Meet New Haven, 1953-1954 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Record department
      - General, 1947-1952 (Box 6, Folder 39)
      - Carrillon Records, 1958-1967 (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Columbia Records and CBS Records, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Complaint about Dillon concert [and other concert information], 1973-1977 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Complaint about station breaks, undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Concert endorsements from politicians, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 44)
      - Concerts held at Yale, 1957-1963 (Box 6, Folder 45)
      - Makeba-Mitchell concert, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 46)
      - Record company information, 1977-1984, undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - Non-musical programming
    - Cinema Around the World, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - College News, Campus News, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence with administration, 1948-1952 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Dwight Hall forums, 1950-1952 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Editorials, 1962-1966 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Freshman show, 1969, n.d (Box 6, Folder 53 - 54)
      General
      See also: Series III. Operations and Administrative Files, 1941-1971 Folder 66
    - Heath Manning Show, undated (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Male Call, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Night Call [national show], 1968 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Senegoid, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Special broadcasts, 1947-1953 (Box 7, Folder 59 - 61)
    - Special broadcasts, discontinued, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - Supplement [English literature show], 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Town and Gown, 1952-1969 (Box 7, Folder 64 - 65)
    - To Your Health, 1948 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Unused scripts, 1954-1957 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Yale Political Union, 1947-1951 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Your Community Speaks, 1964-1966 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Dramatic programming
    - American brotherhood week, undated (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Biography, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Critic's Choice, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Ivy Theatre, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Richard III, undated (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Studio X, 1947-1951, undated (Box 8, Folder 75 - 77)
  - News and political programming
    - General, 1948-1952 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Connecticut Forum of the Air, 1947-1948 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Conservative rally, Madison Square Garden, 1962 (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Election coverage 1956, 1947-1956 (Box 8, Folder 81 - 82)
    - Election coverage 1960, 1956-1960 (Box 9, Folder 83 - 84)
    - Election coverage 1968 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Election coverage 1970, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - May Day coverage [Black Panther trial, student protests at Yale and nationally], 1970 (Box 9, Folder 87 - 92)
    - Monroe, Paul [weekly commentary], 1951 (Box 9, Folder 93)
    - Open debates and lectures, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 94)
    - Perspective for Today, 1951-1952 (Box 9, Folder 95 - 96)
    - Summer news stories [Black Panther trial], [1969] (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - United Press, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Weather, 1971, undated (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - World Today, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - Year-end broadcasts, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 101)
    - Miscellaneous, 1956-1970 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - African-American programming
    - Black Spectrum, 1969-1977 (Box 10, Folder 103)
    - Copies of New Haven Star, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 104)
    - Matchet, Ron, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 105)
    - McLucas, Lonnie [Black Panther trial], 1970 (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Organization of department, undated (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Press releases and news reports, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 108 - 114)
    - Press releases and news reports, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 115 - 125)
    - Reporters' notes [Black Panther trial], [1970] (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - The Way I See It, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - WYBC policies, 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - Public service
    - General, 1947-1952 (Box 12, Folder 130)
    - Say! [proposed public access show], 1974 (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Public relations
    - General, 1954-1958 (Box 12, Folder 132 - 133)
    - Attempt to have NBC broadcast prom, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 134)
    - Audience research, 1960-1967 (Box 12, Folder 135 - 136)
    - "Bladderball", 1959-1966 (Box 12, Folder 137)
    - "King Puff" pipe smoking contest, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 138)
    - Market survey, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 139)
    - Plastic cards promotion [with program schedule], 1961 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - General programming information
    - Broadcast schedules, 1956-1967 (Box 12, Folder 141)
    - Federal Communications Commission engineering test, 1967 (Box 12, Folder 142)
    - Heeler training texts and information sheets, 1964, undated (Box 12, Folder 143)
    - Operating procedures and policies, 1947-1951 (Box 12, Folder 144)
    - Production staff lists, 1948-1949 (Box 13, Folder 145)
    - Shift day outlines and supervisor's lectures, 1960-1966 (Box 13, Folder 146)
    - Station codes and Federal Communications Commission report, Public Service Responsibility of Broadcast Licensees, 1945-1949 (Box 13, Folder 147)
    - WOCD daily program schedules and music sheets, 1945-1946 (Box 13, Folder 148)
    - WYBC daily program schedules, 1948-1949 (Box 13, Folder 149)
    - Miscellaneous, 1956-1976, undated (Box 13, Folder 150 - 153)
- Operations and Administrative Files, 1941-1971; Series III
  This series contains minutes, reports, publications, contracts, schedules, manuals, correspondence and photographs that document the general operation, administration, governance and history of WYBC. The records are arranged alphabetically within WYBC's original headings: Training materials, Technical schematics, Intra-station correspondence, memoranda, and reports, Television station [WYBC-TV], Public relations, Photographs, Legal issues and regulations, Governance, Membership, Fundraising, Financial, WYBC events, Professional organizations, Ivy Network information, and News clippings, scrapbooks.
  - Training materials
    - Announcing instructions and "Continuity", 1945 (Box 14, Folder 1 - 2)
    - Fall training program schedule and engineering instructions, 1969 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Heeler guide originals and department operations, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Heeler Tests, 1957-1969 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Sample supervisor reports, 1960-1968 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Radio Basics and More training manual, undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - WYBC Heeler Guide, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - WYBC-FM [Proposal to convert to FM], 1956-1959 (Box 14, Folder 9 - 10)
  - Automobile policy [Simca 1000], 1966 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Technical schematics
    - Control room two [Master audio schematics], 1956-1958 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Schematic diag. 690 FM exciter, 601/602 trans. control ladder and overload circuit, and transmitter instructions, 1979-1980 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Schematic drawings for WYBC special amplifier chassis, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Station telephone system, undated (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Intra-station correspondence, memoranda, and reports
    - Agnew, Bruce A. [program director], 1950-1966, undated (Box 15, Folder 16 - 19)
    - Confidential chairman's file [advice to incoming WYBC chairmen], 1959-1967 (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Deactivation of members, 1966-1967 (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Departmental reports, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Heeler correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Heeler operations report, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Inactive status requests and deactivation replies, 1969-1970 (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Memos to supervisors, 1947-1948 (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Open letters for WYBC positions, 1966 (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Operations reports, 1952 (Box 15, Folder 28)
    - Personnel forms, undated (Box 15, Folder 29)
    - Program director's confidential division reports, 1950-1951 (Box 15, Folder 30)